Guide to the James Thurber Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Thurber papers
1944-1961
YCAL MSS 546
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.92
(7 boxes)
The James Thurber papers contain drafts and other material relating to three writing projects. The papers feature material relating to Thurber's biographical memoir The Years With Ross (Boston: Little Brown, 1959), about New Yorker founder and publisher Harold Ross. Materials include research material, correspondence, drafts, and proofs. There are also drafts and fan mail for two children's books, Many Moons (New York: Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1943) and The 13 Clocks (New York: Simon and Schuster, 1950).
Thurber, James, 1894-1961
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. James (Helen) Thurber, 1969 and 1971.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
James Thurber Papers (Spec.cms.4), Rare Books and Manuscript Library, Ohio State University.
James Thurber (1894-1961)
James Thurber, humorist, cartoonist, illustrator, and playwright, was born December 8, 1894 in Columbus, Ohio. He graduated from Ohio State University in 1919 and served as a code clerk at the Department of State, Washington, D.C., and at the American Embassy in Paris from 1918 to 1920. In 1927, he joined the staff of The New Yorker, serving first as managing editor, then as a staff writer (1927-1933) and regular contributor (1933-1961). Thurber's writings covered a wide range of genres, including essays, short stories, plays, and children's books, but he is best known for his stories concerning middle-class domestic situations, often based on actual events in his own life. Thurber's book The Years with Ross (1959) is an informal biography of Harold Ross, founder and editor of The New Yorker, as well as a history of the magazine and an account of Thurber's friendship with Ross.
Thurber married twice, in 1922 to Althea Adams (they divorced in 1935) and in 1935 to Helen Muriel Wismer. He had one child, a daughter Rosemary, from his first marriage. Thurber died in New York City on November 2, 1961.
Biographical information drawn from Contemporary Authors Online, Thomson Gale, 2005, s.v. "James Thurber" (accessed 12 May 2011).
Scope and Contents
The James Thurber papers contain drafts and other material relating to the writing projects The Years With Ross, Many Moons, and The 13 Clocks. The papers feature material relating to Thurber's biographical memoir The Years with Ross (1959), about The New Yorker founder and publisher Harold Ross. Materials include research material, correspondence, drafts, and proofs. There are also drafts and fan mail for two children's books, Many Moons (1943) and The 13 Clocks (1950).
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by title.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors; Ross, Harold Wallace, 1892-1951; Thurber, James, 1894-1961
- Many Moons
  - Drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes drawings and proof
  - Fan mail, 1944-1961, undated (Box 1)
- The 13 Clocks
  - Drafts and discards, holograph and typescript, 1951, undated; 6 (Box 1)
  - Fan mail, 1951-1961, undated (Box 1)
- The Years with Ross
  - "Correspondence about Ross series", 1957-1959 (Box 2)
  - "Fan mail", 1958-1960 (Box 2)
  - Draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3)
  - "Original Manuscript Setting Copy," corrected, 1959 (Box 3)
  - "Ross-Thurber letters", 1944-1957; 2 (Box 4)
  - Galley proofs, 1959; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Discarded material", 1957-1958, undated (Box 5)
  - "A note in conclusion", undated (Box 5)
  - "Source material and notes for Ross series", [circa 1953-1958] (Box 5)
  - "Atlantic Monthly correspondence", 1956-1959 (Box 5)
  - "Thurber discards Ross book", 1958 (Box 5)
  - "Copyrights on drawings for Ross book", 1959 (Box 6)
  - Ross foreword and dedication, 1958, undated (Box 6)
  - Drafts, corrected, Chapters I-VIII, 1958, undated; 10 (Box 6)
    Includes galley proofs
  - Drafts, corrected, Chapters IX-XVI, 1958, undated; 8 (Box 7)